Guide to the Records of the Student Army Training Corps 1916-1921 RG 43.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Student Army Training Corps
1916-1921
RG 43.1
New York University Archives
2.0 linear feet (5 boxes)
The records of the Student Army Training Corps Program (SATC) unit are part of the papers of Dean Marshall S. Brown, who served as chairman of NYU's SATC Committee from September 1918 to the following spring. The material includes both internal and external correspondence and memoranda, mainly between the members of NYU's SATC Committee and officials in various government departments.
Brown, Marshall Stewart, 1870-1948
Arrangement
Series are arranged alphabetically.
The records have been organized into three series:
Correspondence and Memoranda
Subject Files
Lists and Reports
Sources
Brown, Marshall S. "Report to the War Department of the Chairman of the Committee on the Students' Army Training Corps," in New York University. Report of Officers, 1918-1919 (New York, 1919) pp. 69-85.
Gruber, Carol S. Mars and Minerva: World War I and the Uses of Higher Learning in America. (Baton Rouge, 1975).
Report of the Chancellor. "Military Training" in New York University. Report of Officers, 1918-1919 (New York, 1919) pp.14-15.
Report of the Treasurer in New York University, Report of Officers, 1918-1919 (New York, 1919) pp. 29-31.
Snow, Charles Henry. The Camp on Campus: The Great War as Observed from a College. Unpublished Manuscript, NYU Archives.
Separated Material
Several items, including a photograph entitled "Presenting the Flag", have been removed from the collection.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Charles Henry Snow Papers, 1917 -1943
William Remington Bryans Papers, 1892 -1954
Scope and Contents
The records of the Student Army Training Corps unit at NYU are part of the papers of Dean Marshall S. Brown, who served as chairman of NYU's SATC Committee from September 1918 to the following spring. The material includes both internal and external correspondence and memoranda, mainly between the members of NYU's SATC Committee and officials in various government departments. Also included are War Department circulars, reports on the condition of the detachment and progress of work, general and special military orders, SATC course handbooks, rosters, and lists of personnel. The bulk of the material falls in the period between March 1918 and December 1918, the period in which the National Army Training Detachment and, later, the SATC were active. However, exploratory material began as early as February 1917, and material relating to the settlement of contracts with the War Department, dismantling of facilities and evaluation of the program extends to June 1919. In addition, there is material relating to the establishment of the Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC), which covers the period from May 1918 to March 1921.
World War I and the Student Army Training Corps are benchmarks in the history of cooperation between the military and educational institutions. The NYU SATC records include material that sheds light on that relationship, including contracts between NYU and the government; material on the development of curricula, most significantly the "War Issues" course; and memoranda offering suggestions for the final report submitted "for the historical record" to the War Department, as well as a copy of the complete report. Announcements, statements of policy, and committee minutes also provide information on the University's participation in the war effort.
Much of the material relates to the day-to-day functioning of the organization. There are highly detailed accounts of the numerical strength of the unit, including daily reports of "changes" in officers and enlisted personnel, muster rolls, and bi-weekly reports of unit strength. These and other rosters and lists of students and applicants shed light on the make-up of the student body and those participating in the program. Letters of application, and applications for discharge often include information on the individual's family and financial status, and provide further indication of the student body and its attitude toward the program.
The large amount of circulars, memoranda, and announcements from the War Department Committee on Education and Special Training, and its district offices, as well as the special organizational chart outlining the activities of the National Army Training Detachment and the SATC, provide information on how the NYU unit fit into the national SATC effort.
History of the Student Army Training Corps at New York University
The Student Army Training Corps (SATC) at New York University was part of a nationwide program initiated by the Committee on Education and Special Training of the War Department during World War I. Begun in the spring of 1918 as the National Army Training Detachments, it was demobilized the following December after the Armistice.
In April 1918 the National Army Training Detachments program was established at 157 colleges, universities, and trade schools under contract with the War Department. The program was designed to train draftees in a variety of trades needed for the war effort, and was jointly administered by the military and the schools. The proposed Student Army Training Corps, according to one historian, would serve to develop "as a great military asset the large body of young men in the colleges and ... [to prevent] unnecessary and wasteful depletion of the colleges through indiscriminate volunteering, by offering the student a definite and immediate military status." (Gruber, Mars and Minerva, p. 215)
Even before the training detachments got underway, the Army realized it lacked the required officers. At the same time, colleges were concerned about the depletion of students by the war and the attendant financial loss, which was only partially redressed by the vocational program. NYU in particular had been financially dependent to a large degree on tuition, much of which was lost by student enlistment.
At NYU Captain (later Major) William S. Maulsby was the military program commander, and Charles Snow, dean of the College of Engineering, was the civilian director of the National Army Training Detachment. Fifteen committees, made up of faculty and staff of the University, were appointed to administer specific areas. The school agreed to provide the soldiers with instruction, food, and quarters. The government, in turn, agreed to reimburse the University a fixed amount per soldier.
The first group of soldiers arrived on April 11 and, together with later inductees, received instruction geared toward becoming auto mechanics, blacksmiths, carpenters, chauffeurs, concrete workers, electricians, machinists, and radio operators. During a two-month period, the men received training in their trades, military instruction and, beginning in July, a course on "War Issues."
At the beginning of the fall semester, 524 institutions enrolled about 140,000 men into SATC units. At that time, the National Army Training Detachments were absorbed into SATC as Section B vocationals. In all, between April 11 and demobilization on December 19, 1918, 1,613 men took part in this section at NYU.
NYU agreed to accept 2,000 men. The NYU SATC unit eventually enrolled 1,564 student-soldiers in two divisions: 1,288 at University Heights and 276 at University and Bellevue Hospital Medical College. Marshall S. Brown, dean of Faculties, was appointed chairman of the SATC Committee and Archibald L. Bouton, dean of the College of Arts and Pure Science, became head of Section A (academics), while Dean Snow continued as head of Section B (vocationals), and Captain Maulsby remained as military commander.
Unlike the "Fighting Mechanics" of the Training Detachments, the collegiate or Section A SATC students were required to fulfill the requirements for college admission and to be accepted as matriculated students by the schools they attended. Inducted as privates in the regular army and subject to military discipline, the student-soldiers lived in barracks, ate at mess and were accorded a monthly allowance of $30 in addition to having their tuition paid. They were to receive a total of 42 hours of "essential" and "allied" subjects while also performing military drill for 11 hours per week. Essential courses included "military law and practice," "hygiene and sanitation," "surveying and map making," "modern ordinance," and the "war issues" course. At the end of their studies (between one and three terms, depending on age), the students were assigned to officer or non-commissioned officer training programs, a depot brigade, or permitted further study in engineering, medicine, or law.
The Armistice interrupted the work of the SATC shortly after it began. After some debate over whether or not it should be continued, the SATC was demobilized on December 19, 1918. Within six months, the work of demobilization and fulfilling contracts between the government and the schools was completed.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers.
Provenance
The SATC program records were presumably transferred to Gould Memorial Library on the University Heights campus of NYU from the Dean of Faculties, Marshall S. Brown. They remained in storage until 1974, when they were transferred to Washington Square following the closing of the Heights campus.
Bouton, Archibald Lewis, 1872-1941; Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934; Brown, Marshall Stewart, 1870-1948; Maulsby, William S.; New York University. College of Medicine.; New York University. National Army Training Detachment.; New York University. Reserve Officer Training Corps.; New York University. School of Applied Science.; New York University. Student Army Training Corps.; New York University. Students.; New York University. Washington Square College of Arts and Science.; Snow, Charles H., (Charles Henry), b. 1863; United States. Army. Students' Army Training Corps.; United States. War Dept. Committee on Education and Special Training.; Contracts.; Curricula.; Military discharges.; Military education |z United States |x History |y 20th century; Minutes.; Muster rolls.; Orders (military records).; Organizational charts.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Series I: Correspondence and Memoranda
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged alphabetically, series includes internal and external communication between the members of the NYU SATC Committee and officers of various governmental departments.
  - American Council on Education, 1918 August - 1918 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Elmer E., [NYU Chancellor], 1917 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Marshall S. [SATC Committee Chairman]
    - General Correspondence, 1918 September - 1918 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, 1918 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, 1918 December - 1919 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bouton, Archibald, 1918 September - 1918 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Maulsby, Commander W. S., 1918 September - 1918 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Park, Dr. W. H., 1918 September - 1918 December (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Snow, Charles H., 1916 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Treasury Department, 1916 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - War Department, Office of the Chief Signal Officer, 1918 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - War Department, Zone Finance Office, 1919 March (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Brown, Elmer E. [NYU Chancellor], 1918 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Brown, Marshall S. [SATC Committee Chairman], 1918 February - 1918 December (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - SATC Headquarters
    - District #2, 1918 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Eastern Department, 1918 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - University Heights, 1918 April - 1918 October (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - University Heights, 1918 November - 1919 April (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - U. S. Army Hospital #1, 1918 May - 1918 August (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - War Department
    - Adjutant General, 1918 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - CEST, General Staff Corps, 1918 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - CEST, Provost Marshal General's Department, 1918 September - 1918 October (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - CEST, War Plans Division
    - Administrative Officer, 1918 May - 1918 September (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Administrative Officer, 1918 October (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Administrative Officer, 1918 November - 1918 December (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Director of College Training, 1918 - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Office of Surgeon General, 1918 November - 1918 December (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series II: Subject Files
  Arranged alphabetically by content, series includes War Department bulletins, circulars, contracts, discharge orders, General, and Special Orders, and University records such as minutes, organizational charts, maps and physical descriptions of barracks, information on the courses taught, and insight into the liquidation of SATC and the formation of an ROTC program.
  - Admissions, SATC: letters of inquiry, 1918 September - 1918 November (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Blank forms, SATC, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bulletin: SATC Headquarters: Eastern Department, 1918 November (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bulletin: SATC Headquarters: University Heights, 1918 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bulletin: Settlement, 1918 -1919 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Certificate, Physical Examination, 1918 November (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Charge Sheets, 1918 July - 1918 December (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Christmas Committee of NYU: SATC Christmas Card, 1918 December (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Circulars: SATC Headquarters, District #2, 1918 November - 1918 December (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Circulars: War Department, General, 1918 - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - War Department, Special Descriptive Circulars, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Contracts: War Department, CEST, 1918 March - 1918 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Contracts: War Department, Office of Surgeon General, 1918 - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Discharge Orders: SATC Headquarters, Eastern Department, 1918 - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Discharge Orders: SATC Headquarters, University Heights, 1918 - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - History of SATC at NYU, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee of the War Council [War Emergency Conference], 1918 February - 1918 June (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: University Committee of SATC, 1918 September (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Naval Section of SATC, 1917 - 1919 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Orders, General: War Department, 1918 September - 1918 October (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Orders, Special: SATC Headquarters: Camp Devens, MA, 1918 May - 1918 June (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Orders, Special: SATC Headquarters: Camp Plattsburg, NY, 1918 May - 1918 October (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Orders, Special: Eastern Department, 1918 - 1919 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Orders, Special: University Heights, 1918 - 1919 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Orders, Special: Various Camps, 1918 April - 1918 October (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Orders, Special: War Department, Adjutant General, 1918 May - 1918 November (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Organization Chart: SATC at NYU, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - ROTC Information, 1918 - 1921 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Selective Service Act: Rules and Regulations, 1918 September (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Settlement and Liquidation OF SATC, 1919 January - 1919 May (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - SATC Buildings, NYU: Description and Map, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - SATC Courses: Human Side of Engineering, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - SATC Courses: Machinists, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - SATC Courses: War Issues, information, 1918 June - 1918 December (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series III: Lists and Reports
  Arranged alphabetically, series includes internal and external communication between the members of the NYU SATC Committee and officers of various governmental departments. [Box 1 and Box 2, folders 1-5]
  - Condition of the Organization Report, 1918 April - 1918 December (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Draft Discharge List, 1918 July - 1918 August (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - List: Engineering Students, 1918 November (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - List: Faculty Teaching SATC courses, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - List: Medical Enlisted Reserve Corps members, 1918 October (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - List: Men Inducted into SATC, 1918 October (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - List: Men Receiving Physical Exams, 1918 November - 1918 December (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - List: Men Recommended for SATC, 1918 October - 1918 November (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - List: Men Rejected as physically unfit for service, 1918 October (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - SATC Student Enrollment, 1918 - 1919 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Students accepted for SATC admission, 1918 October (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Muster Roll, 1918 April - 1918 June (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Payroll Reports: General, 1918 April - 1918 July (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Payroll Reports: General, 1918 August - 1918 October (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Payroll Reports: General, 1918 November - 1918 December (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Final Report, Companies A - I, 1918 December (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Final Report, Special Detachments, 1918 December (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reports: Bi-weekly to CEST, 1918 November (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Reports: Semimonthly to CEST, 1918 November - 1918 December (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Report for Historical Record: SATC at NYU, 1919 January (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Report of Changes: Enlisted Men, 1918 July - 1918 September (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Report of Changes: Enlisted Men, 1918 October (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Report of Changes: Officers, 1918 - 1919 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Roster of NYU Training Detachment, 1918 - 1919 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - School Rating Reports, 1918 May - 1918 October (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Statement of Claim for Reimbursement of Costs, 1918 March - 1918 September (Box 5, Folder 10)